Imprint
-------

**Address**

dus.net GmbH  
Kaiserswerther Str. 215  
D-40474 Düsseldorf

**Company details**

Managing Directors: Udo Ries, Andree Meier  
Commercial register: Düsseldorf Local Court HRB 51060  
Tax number: 105/5810/3243 (FA Düsseldorf-Nord)  
VAT ID No.: DE814260013

**Contact**

eMail: info\[at\]dus\[dot\]net  
Phone: \[+49\] 0211 – 2370 4140  
Fax: \[+49\] 0211 – 2370 4144

**Competent supervisory authority**

Federal Network Agency for Electricity, Gas, Telecommunications, Post and Railway  
Tulip field 4  
53113 Bonn

**Service registration number**

06/289

**Creditor ID No.:**

DE96ZZZ00000840298

Privacy policy
--------------

This data protection declaration informs you about the nature, scope and purpose of the processing of personal data (hereinafter referred to as “data”) within our online offer and the websites, functions and content associated with it, as well as external online presences, such as our social media profiles (hereinafter collectively referred to as “online offer”). With regard to the terms used, such as “processing” or “controller”, we refer to the definitions in Art. 4 of the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR).

### Responsible

dus.net GmbH  
Kaiserswerther Str. 215  
40474 Düsseldorf Germany

E-mail address: info\[at\]dus\[dot\]net  
Managing Directors: Udo Ries, Andree Meier

**Types of data processed:**  

– Inventory data (e.g., names, addresses).  
– Contact information (e.g., email, phone numbers).  
– Payment data (e.g., bank details, payment history, invoices).  
– Content data (e.g., text input, photographs, videos).  
– Usage data (e.g., web pages visited, interest in content, access times).  
– Meta/communication data (e.g., device information, IP addresses).

### Categories of persons concerned

Visitors and users of the online offer (hereinafter we also refer to the data subjects collectively as “users”).

### Purpose of processing

– Provision of the online offer, its functions and contents.  
– Issuance of local telephone numbers (national and international).  
– Porting of local telephone numbers (national and international).  
– the provision of telephone services to the public.  
– Respond to contact requests and communicate with users.  
– Safety measures.  
– Reach measurement/marketing

### Terminology used

“Personal data” means any information relating to an identified or identifiable natural person (hereinafter “data subject”); an identifiable natural person is one who can be identified, directly or indirectly, in particular by reference to an identifier such as a name, an identification number, location data, an online identifier (e.g. cookie) or to one or more factors specific to the physical, physiological, genetic, mental, economic, cultural or social identity of that natural person.

“Processing” means any operation or set of operations which is performed upon Personal Data, whether or not by automatic means. The term is broad and encompasses virtually any handling of data.

“pseudonymization” means the processing of personal data in such a way that the personal data can no longer be attributed to a specific data subject without the use of additional information, provided that such additional information is kept separately and is subject to technical and organizational measures to ensure that the personal data are not attributed to an identified or identifiable natural person.

“profiling” means any automated processing of personal data which consists in using such personal data to evaluate certain personal aspects relating to a natural person, in particular to analyze or predict aspects relating to that natural person’s performance at work, economic situation, health, personal preferences, interests, reliability, behavior, location or change of location.

Controller” means the natural or legal person, public authority, agency or other body which alone or jointly with others determines the purposes and means of the processing of personal data.

“Processor” means a natural or legal person, public authority, agency or other body which processes personal data on behalf of the Controller.

### Relevant legal bases

In accordance with Art. 13 DSGVO, we inform you about the legal basis of our data processing. If the legal basis is not stated in the privacy policy, the following applies: The legal basis for obtaining consent is Art. 6 para. 1 lit. a and Art. 7 DSGVO, the legal basis for processing for the fulfillment of our services and implementation of contractual measures as well as answering inquiries is Art. 6 para. 1 lit. b DSGVO, the legal basis for processing to fulfill our legal obligations is Art. 6 para. 1 lit. c DSGVO, and the legal basis for processing to protect our legitimate interests is Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f GDPR. In the event that vital interests of the data subject or another natural person require the processing of personal data, Art. 6 para. 1 lit. d DSGVO as the legal basis.

### Security measures

We take appropriate technical and organizational measures to ensure a level of protection appropriate to the risk in accordance with Article 32 of the GDPR, taking into account the state of the art, the costs of implementation and the nature, scope, circumstances and purposes of the processing, as well as the varying likelihood and severity of the risk to the rights and freedoms of natural persons.

The measures include, in particular, ensuring the confidentiality, integrity and availability of data by controlling physical access to the data, as well as access to, entry into, disclosure of, assurance of availability of and separation of the data. Furthermore, we have established procedures to ensure the exercise of data subject rights, deletion of data, and response to data compromise. Furthermore, we already take the protection of personal data into account during the development or selection of hardware, software and processes, in accordance with the principle of data protection through technology design and through data protection-friendly default settings (Article 25 of the GDPR).

### Cooperation with processors and third parties

If, in the course of our processing, we disclose data to other persons and companies (processors or third parties), transmit it to them or otherwise grant them access to the data, this will only be done on the basis of a legal permission (e.g. if a transmission of the data to third parties, such as to payment service providers, is required for the performance of the contract pursuant to Art. 6 (1) lit. b DSGVO), you have consented, a legal obligation provides for this or on the basis of our legitimate interests (e.g. when using agents, web hosts, etc.).

If we commission third parties with the processing of data on the basis of a so-called “order processing agreement”, this is done on the basis of Art. 28 DSGVO.

### Transfers to third countries

If we process data in a third country (i.e. outside the European Union (EU) or the European Economic Area (EEA)) or if this is done in the context of using third-party services or disclosing or transferring data to third parties, this will only be done if it is done to fulfill our (pre-)contractual obligations, on the basis of your consent, due to a legal obligation or on the basis of our legitimate interests. Subject to legal or contractual permissions, we process or allow the processing of data in a third country only if the special requirements of Art. 44 et seq. DSGVO are met. This means, for example, that processing takes place on the basis of special guarantees, such as the officially recognized determination of a level of data protection that corresponds to that of the EU (e.g., for the USA through the “Privacy Shield”) or compliance with officially recognized special contractual obligations (so-called “standard contractual clauses”).

### Rights of the data subjects

You have the right to request confirmation as to whether data in question is being processed and to information about this data, as well as further information and a copy of the data in accordance with Art. 15 DSGVO.

You have accordingly. Art. 16 DSGVO the right to request the completion of the data concerning you or the correction of incorrect data concerning you.

In accordance with Article 17 of the GDPR, you have the right to demand that the data in question be deleted without delay or, alternatively, to demand restriction of the processing of the data in accordance with Article 18 of the GDPR.

You have the right to request to receive the data concerning you that you have provided to us in accordance with Article 20 of the GDPR and to request its transfer to other data controllers.

They have further pursuant to Article 77 DSGVO the right to lodge a complaint with the competent supervisory authority.

### Right of withdrawal

You have the right to withdraw consent granted pursuant to. Art. 7 par. 3 DSGVO with effect for the future

### Right of objection

You may object to the future processing of data concerning you in accordance with Art. 21 DSGVO at any time. The objection can be made in particular against the processing for purposes of direct advertising.

### Cookies and right to object to direct advertising

Cookies” are small files that are stored on users’ computers. Different information can be stored within the cookies. The primary purpose of a cookie is to store information about a user (or the device on which the cookie is stored) during or after his visit within an online offer. Temporary cookies, or “session cookies” or “transient cookies”, are cookies that are deleted after a user leaves an online offer and closes his browser. In such a cookie, for example, the contents of a shopping cart in an online store or a login status can be stored. Permanent” or “persistent” cookies are those that remain stored even after the browser is closed. For example, the login status can be saved when users visit them after several days. Likewise, such a cookie may store the interests of users, which are used for reach measurement or marketing purposes. Third-party cookies” are cookies that are offered by providers other than the responsible party that operates the online offer (otherwise, if they are only its cookies, they are referred to as “first-party cookies”).

We may use temporary and permanent cookies and explain this in our privacy policy.

If users do not want cookies to be stored on their computer, they are asked to disable the corresponding option in the system settings of their browser. Stored cookies can be deleted in the system settings of the browser. The exclusion of cookies results in **functional restrictions of this online offer**.

A general objection to the use of cookies used for online marketing purposes can be declared for a large number of the services, especially in the case of tracking, via the U.S. site [http://www.aboutads.info/choices/](http://www.aboutads.info/choices/) or the EU site [http://www.youronlinechoices.com/](http://www.youronlinechoices.com/). Furthermore, the storage of cookies can be achieved by means of their deactivation in the browser settings. Please note that in this case not all functions of this online offer can be used.

### Data deletion

The data processed by us will be deleted or restricted in its processing in accordance with Articles 17 and 18 DSGVO. Unless expressly stated within the scope of this data protection declaration, the data stored by us will be deleted as soon as they are no longer required for their intended purpose and the deletion does not conflict with any statutory retention obligations. If the data are not deleted because they are required for other and legally permissible purposes, their processing will be restricted. I.e. the data is blocked and not processed for other purposes. This applies, for example, to data that must be retained for reasons of commercial or tax law.

According to legal requirements in Germany, the storage takes place in particular for 10 years according to §§ 147 Abs. 1 AO, 257 para. 1 No. 1 and 4, para. 4 HGB (books, records, management reports, accounting vouchers, commercial books, documents relevant for taxation, etc.) and 6 years according to § 257 para. 1 No. 2 and 3, para. 4 HGB (Commercial Letters).

According to legal requirements in Austria, the storage is carried out in particular for 7 years in accordance with § 132 para. 1 BAO (accounting records, vouchers/invoices, accounts, receipts, business papers, statement of income and expenses, etc.), for 22 years in connection with real property, and for 10 years for records in connection with electronically provided services, telecommunications, radio and television services provided to non-entrepreneurs in EU member states and for which the Mini-One-Stop-Shop (MOSS) is used.

### Business processing

In addition we process  
– Contract data (e.g., subject matter of the contract, term, customer category).  
– Payment data (e.g., bank details, payment history)  
from our customers, prospective customers and business partners for the purpose of providing contractual services, service and customer care, marketing and advertising on our own behalf.

### Contractual services

We process the data of our contractual partners and interested parties as well as other clients, customers, clients or contractual partners (uniformly referred to as “contractual partners”) in accordance with Art. 6 para. 1 lit. b. DSGVO in order to provide them with our contractual or pre-contractual services. The data processed in this context, the type, scope and purpose and the necessity of their processing, are determined by the underlying contractual relationship.

The processed data includes the master data of our contractual partners (e.g., names and addresses), contact data (e.g., e-mail addresses and telephone numbers) as well as contract data (e.g., services used, contract contents, contractual communication, names of contact persons) and payment data (e.g., bank details, payment history).

As a matter of principle, we do not process special categories of personal data, unless these are components of a commissioned or contractual processing (e.g., the date of birth in the case of telephone number assignment or telephone number porting of private individuals).

We process data that are necessary for the justification and fulfillment of the contractual services and point out the necessity of their indication, if this is not evident for the contractual partners. Disclosure to external persons or companies will only be made if it is required as part of a contract. When processing the data provided to us as part of an order, we act in accordance with the instructions of the client and the legal requirements.

When using our online services, we may store the IP address and the time of the respective user action. The storage is based on our legitimate interests, as well as the interests of users in protection against misuse and other unauthorized use. In principle, this data will not be passed on to third parties, unless it is necessary for the pursuit of our claims in accordance with the German Data Protection Act. Art. 6 par. 1 lit. f. DSGVO is required or there is a legal obligation to do so pursuant to. Art. 6 par. 1 lit. c. GDPR.

The deletion of the data takes place when the data is no longer required for the fulfillment of contractual or legal duties of care as well as for dealing with any warranty and comparable obligations, whereby the necessity of retaining the data is reviewed every three years; otherwise, the legal retention obligations apply.

### External payment service providers

We use external payment service providers through whose platforms the users and we can make payment transactions (e.g., each with a link to the privacy policy, Paypal (https://www.paypal.com/de/webapps/mpp/ua/privacy-full), Klarna (https://www.klarna.com/de/datenschutz/), Skrill (https://www.skrill.com/de/fusszeile/datenschutzrichtlinie/), Giropay (https://www.giropay.de/rechtliches/datenschutz-agb/), Visa (https://www.visa.de/datenschutz), Mastercard (https://www.mastercard.de/de-de/datenschutz.html), American Express (https://www.americanexpress.com/de/content/privacy-policy-statement.html)

In the context of the fulfillment of contracts, we use the payment service providers on the basis of Art. 6 para. 1 lit. b. GDPR on. In addition, we use external payment service providers on the basis of our legitimate interests pursuant to Art. Art. 6 par. 1 lit. f. DSGVO to provide our users with effective and secure payment options. The possibility of issuing a SEPA direct debit mandate from the user or a user-initiated bank transfer is also, depending on what is contractually agreed, remains.

The data processed by the payment service providers includes inventory data, such as name and address, bank data, such as account numbers or credit card numbers, passwords, TANs and checksums, as well as contract, total and recipient-related data. The information is necessary to carry out the transactions. However, the data entered is only processed by the payment service providers and stored with them. I.e. we do not receive any account or credit card related information, but only information with confirmation or negative information of the payment. Under certain circumstances, the data may be transmitted by the payment service providers to credit agencies. The purpose of this transmission is to check identity and creditworthiness. In this regard, we refer to the terms and conditions and data protection information of the payment service providers.

The terms and conditions and the data protection notices of the respective payment service providers apply to the payment transactions, which can be accessed within the respective websites or transaction applications. We also refer to these for further information and assertion of revocation, information and other data subject rights.

### Registration function (ordering a product)

Users can create a user account. As part of the registration process, the required mandatory information is provided to users and processed on the basis of Art. 6 para. 1 lit. b DSGVO for the purpose of providing the user account and the ordered products. The processed data includes in particular the login information (name, password as well as an e-mail address). The data entered during registration will be used for the purposes of using the user account and its purpose.

Users may be notified of information relevant to their user account, such as technical changes, by email. If users have terminated their user account, their data relating to the user account will be deleted, subject to any legal obligation to retain such data. It is the responsibility of the users to back up their data before the end of the contract if the contract has been terminated. We are entitled to irretrievably delete all of the user’s data stored during the term of the contract.

In the context of the use of our registration and login functions as well as the use of the user account, we store the IP address and the time of the respective user action. The storage is based on our legitimate interests, as well as those of users in protection against misuse and other unauthorized use. As a matter of principle, this data will not be passed on to third parties unless it is necessary for the prosecution of our claims or there is a legal obligation to do so in accordance with the German Data Protection Act. Art. 6 par. 1 lit. c GDPR. The IP addresses are anonymized or deleted after 7 days at the latest.

### Comments and contributions

When users leave comments or other contributions, their IP addresses may be stored on the basis of our legitimate interests as defined in Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f. DSGVO are stored for 7 days. This is done for our security, in case someone leaves illegal content in comments and posts (insults, forbidden political propaganda, etc.). In this case, we ourselves may be prosecuted for the comment or post and are therefore interested in the identity of the author.

Furthermore, we reserve the right, on the basis of our legitimate interests pursuant to sec. Art. 6 par. 1 lit. f. DSGVO to process the information of the users for the purpose of spam detection.

On the same legal basis, we reserve the right, in the case of surveys, to store the IP addresses of users for their duration and to use Cookis to avoid multiple votes.

The data provided as part of the comments and contributions, will be stored by us permanently until the user objects.

### Contact

When contacting us (e.g. by contact form, e-mail, telephone or via social media), the user’s details will be used to process the contact request and its handling in accordance with the German Data Protection Act. Art. 6 par. 1 lit. b) DSGVO processed. User information may be stored in a customer relationship management system (“CRM System”) or similar inquiry organization.

We delete the requests if they are no longer necessary. We review the necessity every two years; Furthermore, the legal archiving obligations apply.

### Newsletter

With the following information we inform you about the contents of our newsletter as well as the registration, dispatch and statistical evaluation procedure and your rights of objection. By subscribing to our newsletter, you agree to receive it and to the procedures described.

Newsletter content: We send newsletters, e-mails and other electronic notifications with promotional information (hereinafter “newsletter”) only with the consent of the recipients or a legal permission. Insofar as the contents of the newsletter are specifically described in the course of registration, they are decisive for the user’s consent. For the rest, our newsletters contain information about our services and us.

Double-Opt-In and logging: The registration for our newsletter takes place in a so-called double-opt-in process. I.e. after registration you will receive an email asking you to confirm your registration. This confirmation is necessary so that no one can log in with foreign e-mail addresses. Subscriptions to the newsletter are logged in order to be able to prove the subscription process in accordance with legal requirements. This includes the storage of the login and confirmation time, as well as the IP address. Likewise, changes to your data stored with the shipping service provider are logged.

Registration data: To register for the newsletter, it is sufficient to provide your e-mail address. Optionally, we ask you to enter a name for the purpose of personal address in the newsletter.

The dispatch of the newsletter and the associated performance measurement are based on the consent of the recipients in accordance with. Art. 6 par. 1 lit. a, Art. 7 DSGVO in conjunction with § 7 para. 2 No. 3 UWG or, if consent is not required, on the basis of our legitimate interests in direct marketing pursuant to. Art. 6 par. 1 lt. f. DSGVO in conjunction with. § 7 para. 3 UWG.

The logging of the registration process takes place on the basis of our legitimate interests in accordance with. Art. 6 par. 1 lit. f GDPR. We are interested in using a user-friendly and secure newsletter system that serves our business interests, meets the expectations of users, and allows us to prove consent.

Cancellation/Revocation – You can cancel the receipt of our newsletter at any time, i.e. revoke your consents. You will find a link to cancel the newsletter at the end of each newsletter. We may store unsubscribed email addresses for up to three years based on our legitimate interests before deleting them to be able to prove consent formerly given. The processing of this data is limited to the purpose of a possible defense against claims. An individual deletion request is possible at any time, provided that the former existence of consent is confirmed at the same time.

### Newsletter – Success measurement

The newsletters contain a so-called “web beacon”, i.e. a pixel-sized file that is retrieved from our server or, if we use a shipping service provider, from their server when the newsletter is opened. Within the scope of this retrieval, technical information, such as information about the browser and your system, as well as your IP address and the time of the retrieval are initially collected.

This information is used for the technical improvement of the services based on the technical data or the target groups and their reading behavior based on their retrieval locations (which can be determined with the help of the IP address) or the access times. Statistical surveys also include determining whether newsletters are opened, when they are opened, and which links are clicked. For technical reasons, this information can be assigned to individual newsletter recipients. However, it is neither our intention nor, if used, that of the shipping service provider to monitor individual users. The evaluations serve us much more to recognize the reading habits of our users and to adapt our content to them or to send different content according to the interests of our users.

A separate revocation of the performance measurement is unfortunately not possible, in this case the entire newsletter subscription must be cancelled.

### Hosting and emailing

The hosting services operated by us serve to provide the following services: Infrastructure and platform services, computing capacity, storage space and database services, e-mail dispatch, security services and technical maintenance services, which we use for the purpose of operating this online offering and providing our products.

In doing so, we process inventory data, contact data, content data, contract data, usage data, meta data and communication data of customers, interested parties and visitors of this online offer on the basis of our legitimate interests in an efficient and secure provision of this online offer in accordance with the German Data Protection Act. Art. 6 par. 1 lit. f DSGVO in conjunction with. Art. 28 DSGVO (conclusion of order processing contract).

### Collection of access data and log files

We, on the basis of our legitimate interests within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f. DSGVO data about each access to the server on which this service is located (so-called server log files). The access data includes the name of the website accessed, file, date and time of access, amount of data transferred, notification of successful access, browser type and version, the user’s operating system, referrer URL (the previously visited page), IP address and the requesting provider.

Log file information is stored for security reasons (e.g. for the clarification of abuse or fraud) for a maximum of 7 days and then deleted. Data whose further retention is required for evidentiary purposes is exempt from deletion until final clarification of the respective incident.

### Google Analytics

We use Google Analytics, a web analytics service provided by Google LLC (“Google”), on the basis of our legitimate interests (i.e. interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our online offering within the meaning of Art. 6 (1) lit. f. DSGVO) Google Analytics, a web analytics service provided by Google LLC (“Google”). Google uses cookies. The information generated by the cookie about the use of the online offer by the user is usually transmitted to a Google server in the USA and stored there.

Google is certified under the Privacy Shield agreement and thereby offers a guarantee of compliance with European data protection law[(https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt000000001L5AAI&status=Active)](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt000000001L5AAI&status=Active).

Google will use this information on our behalf for the purpose of evaluating your use of our website, compiling reports on website activity for website operators and providing other services relating to website activity and internet usage. In doing so, pseudonymous usage profiles of the users can be created from the processed data.

We use Google Analytics only with IP anonymization enabled. This means that the IP address of the user is shortened by Google within member states of the European Union or in other contracting states of the Agreement on the European Economic Area. Only in exceptional cases is the full IP address transmitted to a Google server in the USA and shortened there.

The IP address transmitted by the user’s browser is not merged with other data from Google. Users can prevent the storage of cookies by setting their browser software accordingly; users can also prevent the collection of the data generated by the cookie and related to their use of the online offer to Google as well as the processing of this data by Google by downloading and installing the browser plugin available under the following link: [http://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=de.](http://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=de)

For more information about Google’s use of data, settings and opt-out options, please refer to Google’s privacy policy[(https://policies.google.com/technologies/ads)](https://policies.google.com/technologies/ads) and the settings for the display of advertisements by Google [(https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated)](https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated).

Users’ personal data is deleted or anonymized after 14 months.

### Google AdWords and conversion measurement

We use the services of Google LLC, 1600 Amphitheatre Park Park Mountain View, CA 9.0.2008 (“Google”) on the basis of our legitimate interests (i.e. interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our online offer within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f. DSGVO). DSGVO) the services of Google LLC, 1600 Amphitheatre Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA, (“Google”).

Google is certified under the Privacy Shield agreement and thereby offers a guarantee of compliance with European data protection law (https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt000000001L5AAI&status=Active).

We use the online marketing method Google “AdWords” to place ads in the Google advertising network (e.g., in search results, in videos, on web pages, etc.) so that they are displayed to users who have a presumed interest in the ads. This allows us to display ads for and within our online offering in a more targeted manner in order to only present users with ads that potentially match their interests. If, for example, a user is shown ads for products he or she was interested in on other online offers, this is referred to as “remarketing”. For these purposes, when our website and other websites on which the Google advertising network is active are called up, a code is executed directly by Google and so-called (re)marketing tags (invisible graphics or code, also referred to as “web beacons”) are integrated into the website. With their help, an individual cookie, i.e. a small file, is stored on the user’s device (comparable technologies can also be used instead of cookies). This file records which web pages the user has visited, which content the user is interested in and which offers the user has clicked on, as well as technical information about the browser and operating system, referring web pages, time of visit and other information about the use of the online offer.

Furthermore, we receive an individual “conversion cookie”. The information obtained with the help of the cookie is used by Google to create conversion statistics for us. However, we only learn the anonymous total number of users who clicked on our ad and were redirected to a page tagged with a conversion tracking tag. However, we do not receive any information that personally identifies users.

User data is processed pseudonymously within the Google advertising network. I.e. Google does not store and process e.g. the name or email address of the users, but processes the relevant data cookie-related within pseudonymous user profiles. I.e. from Google’s point of view, the ads are not managed and displayed for a specifically identified person, but for the cookie holder, regardless of who this cookie holder is. This does not apply if a user has expressly allowed Google to process the data without this pseudonymization. The information collected about users is transmitted to Google and stored on Google’s servers in the USA.

For more information about Google’s use of data, settings and opt-out options, please refer to Google’s privacy policy[(https://policies.google.com/technologies/ads)](https://policies.google.com/technologies/ads) and the settings for the display of advertisements by Google [(https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated)](https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated).

### Integration of third-party services and content

Within our online offer, we use content or service offers of third-party providers on the basis of our legitimate interests (i.e. interest in the analysis, optimization and economic operation of our online offer within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 lit. f. DSGVO) content or service offers from third-party providers in order to integrate their content and services, such as videos or fonts (hereinafter uniformly referred to as “content”).

This always assumes that the third-party providers of this content are aware of the IP address of the user, since without the IP address they would not be able to send the content to their browser. The IP address is thus required for the display of this content. We endeavor to use only such content whose respective providers use the IP address only for the delivery of the content. Third-party providers may also use so-called pixel tags (invisible graphics, also known as “web beacons”) for statistical or marketing purposes. The “pixel tags” can be used to evaluate information such as visitor traffic on the pages of this website. The pseudonymous information may also be stored in cookies on the user’s device and may contain, among other things, technical information about the browser and operating system, referring websites, time of visit and other information about the use of our online offer, as well as be combined with such information from other sources.

### Google Fonts

We integrate the fonts (“Google Fonts”) of the provider Google LLC, 1600 Amphitheatre Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA. Privacy Policy: [https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/,](https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/) Opt-Out: [https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated.](https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated)

### Google ReCaptcha

We integrate the function for the recognition of bots, e.g. for entries in online forms (“ReCaptcha”) of the provider Google LLC, 1600 Amphitheatre Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA. Privacy Policy: [https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/,](https://www.google.com/policies/privacy/) Opt-Out: [https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated.](https://adssettings.google.com/authenticated)

### Twitter

Within our online offer, functions and contents of the service Twitter, offered by Twitter Inc., 1355 Market Street, Suite 900, San Francisco, CA 94103, USA, may be integrated. This may include, for example, content such as images, videos or texts and buttons with which users can share content of this online offer within Twitter.  
If the users are members of the Twitter platform, Twitter can assign the call of the above-mentioned content and functions to the profiles of the users there. Twitter is certified under the Privacy Shield agreement and thereby offers a guarantee of compliance with European data protection law[(https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000TORzAAO&status=Active)](https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000TORzAAO&status=Active). Privacy Policy: [https://twitter.com/de/privacy,](https://twitter.com/de/privacy) Opt-Out: [https://twitter.com/personalization.](https://twitter.com/personalization)

#### General

#### Legal

#### Help

© 2004-2023 dus.net GmbH. Alle Rechte vorbehalten.

We use cookies to give you the best possible experience on our website.  
In the Settings you can find out which cookies we are using or switch them off.

Accept Reject Settings

                          Cookie-Settings

Close GDPR Cookie Settings

* Privacy Overview
* Unbedingt notwendige Cookies
* Third Party Cookies
* Cookie Policy

Privacy Overview

This website uses cookies so that we can offer you the best possible user experience. Cookie information is stored in your browser and performs functions such as recognizing you when you return to our website and helping our team to understand which sections of the website you find most interesting and useful.

Unbedingt notwendige Cookies

Strictly Necessary Cookie should be enabled at all times so that we can save your preferences for cookie settings.

Enable or Disable Cookies 

Third Party Cookies

This website uses Google Analytics to collect anonymous information such as the number of visitors to the site and the most popular pages.

Keeping this cookie enabled helps us to improve our website.

Enable or Disable Cookies 

Please enable Strictly Necessary Cookies first so that we can save your preferences!

Cookie Policy

More information about our [cookie policy](https://www.dus.net/en/imprint "Imprint").

Activate all Reject all Save changes
